Guide to the Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean (EPICA) records, 1960s-2005 RL.11660
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean (EPICA) records
1960s-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.11660
6 Linear Feet
Clippings, reports, publications, and photographs from Puerto Rico, Jamaica, Dominican Repulic, Grenada, and other Caribbean countries, collected and produced by the Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean (EPICA). Materials document human rights, government and democracy, and labor conditions in the Caribbean, and largely date from the 1970s and 1980s.
Arrangement
Arranged into series: Country Files, arranged geographically by country; Publications, listed by title.
Biographical / Historical
EPICA was originally founded in 1968, as the Ecumenical Program for Inter-American Communication and Action. It aimed to provide resources for political and economic analysis, spiritual reflection and social action, projecting the voices, perspectives and movements of the global South; strengthen ties of solidarity with grassroots organizations and movements in the global South; raise critical awareness among people of the United States about the impact of corporate globalization, neo-liberalism and militarism in the Americas and the struggle of the poor to create just and peaceful alternatives; mobilize constituencies to challenge USA, corporate and global institutions that cause economic injustice, violence and exclusion in the Americas.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018 and 2020.
Collection Overview
The EPICA collection consists of approximately 4 linear feet of material contained in four cartons. Countries represented include Jamaica, the Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico, Cuba, Haiti, Grenada, and the French Antilles. Within each box, documents are in folders labeled by country and year(s), about 10-15 folders per country.
The documents were collected in the Caribbean by staff of EPICA (Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean, a small DC-based group originally funded mainly by the Latin American and Caribbean Office of the National Council of Churches, but no longer operating). The founder and first director of EPICA was the Rev. Philip E. Wheaton.
The documents include newsletters, leaflets, position statements, advocacy materials, analytical papers, and the like, from grassroots groups, political parties, church bodies, academics, etc. Most of the material is from the 1970s and 1980s, with a small amount from the early 1990s.
For each country there is also a folder of notes from interviews with grassroots activists, political party figures, academics, journalists, trade unionists, etc. These are not transcripts, as the interviews were not taped, but handwritten notes on what the person said.
In addition, there are printed materials, mostly publications by EPICA.
Caribbean Area -- 20th century; Sugar trade -- Jamaica; Jamaica -- History; Human Rights; Grenada -- 20th century; Jamaica -- Politics and government -- 1962-; Grenada -- History -- American Invasion, 1983; Puerto Rico -- Politics and government -- 20th century; West Indies, French -- History -- 20th century; Haiti -- History -- 20th century; Dominican Republic -- History -- 20th century; Caribbean Area -- Pictorial works; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Country Files, 1960s-1990s
  Scope and Contents
  Country Files were collected, arranged, and preserved by EPICA staff. The documents include newsletters, leaflets, position statements, advocacy materials, analytical papers, and the like, from grassroots groups, political parties, church bodies, academics, etc.
  For most countries there is also a folder of notes from interviews, largely conducted by Catherine Sunshine with grassroots activists, political party figures, academics, journalists, trade unionists, etc. These are not transcripts, as the interviews were not taped, but handwritten notes on what the person said. The interviewee's identification is included when known.
  Some countries also include an assortment of photographs; most are reference images or copies and include captions from various publications or archives.
  - Dominican Republic interview notes, 1983, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Antonio Aquino, 1986 (Box 1)
      Secretary General, Central General de Trabajadores (CGT). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Eduardo Díaz Guerra, 1983 (Box 1)
      Editor, Revista CEPAE, magazine of Centro de Planificación y Acción Ecuménica (CEPAE). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Juan Bolívar Díaz, 1983 (Box 1)
      Editor, El Nuevo Diario newspaper, Santo Domingo. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Unidentified, 1986 (Box 1)
      Informants in Hato Damas, San Cristóbal, Dominican Republic. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Rosario Espinal, 1986 (Box 1)
      Sociologist, political analyst, human rights activist. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Antonio Florián, 1986 (Box 1)
      Leadership, Federación Nacional de Trabajadores Azucareros, Agrícolas y Afines (FENAZUCAR). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Santiago Hirujo Sosa, 1983 (Box 1)
      Journalist, El Nuevo Diario newspaper, Santo Domingo; Catholic priest. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Ramón Jiménez, 1986 (Box 1)
      Movimiento Campesino Independiente (MCI). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Unidentified, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Elvidia Moronta de Martínez, 1986 (Box 1)
      Comité para la Defensa de los Derechos Barriales (COPADEBA). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Octavio Rivera, 1983 (Box 1)
      Comité Político del Bloque Socialista. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Santiago Sosa Castillo, 1986 (Box 1)
      Executive secretary of Centro de Planificación y Acción Ecuménica (CEPAE). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Claudio Tavarez Belliard, 1983 (Box 1)
      Activist. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
  - Dominican Republic chronological files, 1964-1990s; 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Dominican Republic photographs, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Jamaica interview notes, 1982-1987 (Box 2)
    - Neville Duncan, 1982 (Box 2)
      Chair, Dept. of Government, University of the West Indies, Cave Hill, Barbados. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Don Robotham, 1983 (Box 2)
      Founding member, Workers Party of Jamaica. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Wesley Hughes, 1983 (Box 2)
      Director of economics and statistics, Jamaica Bauxite Institute. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Dorrit Bent, 1983 (Box 2)
      Caribbean Conference of Churches Women's Program. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Horace Levy, 1983 (Box 2)
      Director, Social Action Centre, Kingston. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Horace Levy, 1984 (Box 2)
      Director, Social Action Centre, Kingston. Interviewed by Don Foster.
    - Michael Witter, 1984 (Box 2)
      Economist and lecturer, University of the West Indies, Mona, Jamaica. Interviewed by Don Foster.
    - Anthony Bogues, 1984 (Box 2)
      Political education secretary and executive member, People's National Party. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Anthony Bogues, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Michael Thelwell, 1986 (Box 2)
      Novelist, screenwriter, civil rights activist. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Beverley Manley, 1987 (Box 2)
      Former first lady of Jamaica, PNP activist. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
  - Jamaica chronological files, 1973-1991; 16 folders (Box 2)
  - Jamaica photographs, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Puerto Rico interview notes, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
    - Juan Manuel Carrión, 1984 (Box 2)
      President, board of directors, Center for Study of the Puerto Rican Reality (CEREP). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Juan Castañer, 1986 (Box 2)
      Center for Study of the Puerto Rican Reality (CEREP). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Carmen Gautier Mayoral, 1987 (Box 2)
      Professor and director, Social Science Research Center, University of Puerto Rico. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Alfonso Román Morales, 1983 (Box 2)
      National Ecumenical Movement of Puerto Rico (PRISA). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
    - Eunice Santana Melecio, 1983 (Box 2)
      Coordinator, National Ecumenical Movement of Puerto Rico (PRISA). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine.
  - Puerto Rico chronological files, 1960s-1974; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Puerto Rico chronological files, 1975-1999; 16 folders (Box 3)
  - Puerto Rico: Libros Para el Pueblo, published by Division de Educacion de la Comunidad in the Depto. de Instruccion Publica, 1954-1969; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Booklets (incomplete set) edited and authored (in part) by Rene Marques. Includes: De como se vive en distintas partes del mundo (number 2, 1966); 5 Cuentos de miedo (number 6, 1966); El nino y su mundo (number 7, 1954); La Familia (number 9, 1967); Los Derechos del Hombre (number 10, 1968); 4 Cuentos de mujeres (number 13, 1967); Lucha Obrera (number 15, undated); Las Manos y el Ingenio del Hombre (number 23, 1966); Las Ideas, los Otros, y Yo (number 23, 1966); Nuestros Hijos (number 24, 1966); Isla y Pueblo (number 28, 1968); Liderato (number 29, 1969); Que Sabemos del Huracan? (unnumbered, undated)
  - French Antilles interview notes, 1982-1987 (Box 4)
    - Frantz Succab, 1987 (Box 4)
      Ja Ka Ta magazine; independence activist. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Jacques Adélaïde Merlande, 1987 (Box 4)
      Historian. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Martinique.
    - Père Pierre Fertin, 1987 (Box 4)
      Catholic priest; editor, Information Caraib newsletter. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Dany Bébel-Gisler, 1982 (Box 4)
      Linguist, sociologist, educator; researcher with Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Gilbert Pago, 1984 (Box 4)
      Member of political bureau of Groupe Révolution Socialiste (GRS). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Martinique.
    - Nikol (Nicol) Verepla, 1987 (Box 4)
      Primary school teacher; member of Chrétiens pour la Libération du Peuple Guadeloupéen. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Gilbert Bienville, 1982 (Box 4)
      Chrétiens pour la Libération du Peuple Guadeloupéen. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Père Serge Plocoste, 1982 (Box 4)
      Catholic priest; Jeunesse Ouvrière Chrétienne. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Père Serge Plocoste, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Père Albert Blanchard, 1987 (Box 4)
      Catholic priest. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Frantz Narbonnais, 1987 (Box 4)
      Teacher. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Sr. Marcelle Wachter, 1982 (Box 4)
      Catholic sister, Presbytère Baie-Mahault. Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Sr. Marcelle Wachter, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Père Chérubin Céleste, 1982 (Box 4)
      Catholic priest, activist, led Mouvement Rural des Jeunesses Chrétiennes (MRJC). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
    - Unidentified, 1982 (Box 4)
      Union Populaire pour la Libération de la Guadeloupe (UPLG). Interviewed by Catherine Sunshine, Guadeloupe.
  - French Antilles chronological files, 1978-1987; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - French Antilles photographs, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Haiti chronological files, 1989-1998; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Trinidad and Tobago chronological file, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Guyana chronological file, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Grenada photographs, 1980s; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Includes set of photographs (and negatives) taken by Catherine Sunshine (1980-1982) and used in EPICA publication "Grenada: The Peaceful Revolution" publication (c. 1982). Also includes official U.S. Defense Dept. and White House photographs from the 1983 Marine invasion of Grenada. Also includes snapshots of Grenadians and library reproductions of photographs from colonial period (1915 and 1953).
- EPICA publications, 1979-2005
  Bound printed publications, largely published by EPICA and its partners. Includes reference and educational materials about Caribbean countries and people in Jamaica, Puerto Rico, and Grenada, as well as regional discussions of politics, independence, and culture.
  - EPICA Task Force. Jamaica: Caribbean Challenge. A People's Primer, 1979 (Box 4)
  - EPICA Task Force. Puerto Rico: A People Challenging Colonialism. A People's Primer, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Sunshine, Catherine A., and EPICA. The Caribbean: Survival, Struggle, and Sovereignty, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Wheaton, Philip, and EPICA. The Iron Triangle: The Honduran Connection, 1981 (Box 4)
  - EPICA Task Force. Grenada: The Peaceful Revolution, 1982 (Box 4)
  - EPICA and Network of Educators' Committees on Central America. Caribbean Connections: Classroom Resources for Secondary Schools. Overview of Regional History, 1991 (Box 4)
  - EPICA and Network of Educators' Committees on Central America. Caribbean Connections: Classroom Resources for Secondary Schools. Puerto Rico, 1990 (Box 4)
  - EPICA and Network of Educators' Committees on Central America. Caribbean Connections: Classroom Resources for Secondary Schools. Jamaica, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Racine, Marie M. B. and EPICA. Like the Dew that Waters the Grass: Words from Haitian Women, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Johnson, Fay Clarke. Soldiers of the Soil (New York: Vantage Press), 1995. (Box 4)
  - Sistren Theatre Collective, edited by Honor Ford Smith. Lionheart Gal: Life Stories of Jamaican Women (London: Women's Press), 1986. (Box 4)
  - Teaching for Change (Washington DC). Caribbean Connections: Moving North, 2005 (Box 4)